Guide to the Bruce Nelson Research Files on Maritime Workers TAM.585
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Bruce Nelson Research Files on Maritime Workers
1931-2011
TAM.585
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
Historian Bruce Nelson is the author of Workers on the Waterfront: Seamen, Longshoremen, and Unionism in the 1930s (1990). This collection contains files on prominent radical sailors who were members of the National Maritime Union, and files on several maritime labor events and on related organizations. The files include Nelson's correspondence with these sailors, detailed summaries (or, in the case of Joseph Stack, transcripts) of oral histories, printed ephemera and internal National Maritime Union documents, in particular from the post-World War II period of internal struggle between the union's Communist and anti-Communist factions.
Nelson, Bruce, 1940-
Box 1-2
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Historian Bruce Nelson is the author of Workers on the Waterfront: Seamen, Longshoremen, and Unionism in the 1930s (1990) and Professor Emeritus at Dartmouth College.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains materials compiled or created by Bruce Nelson in connection with his research for his book Workers on the Waterfront: Seamen, Longshoremen, and Unionism in the 1930s (1990). Most of the files are on notable radical maritime activists, and include correspondence with them, detailed summaries (or, in the case of Joseph Stack, transcripts) of oral histories, printed ephemera and internal National Maritime Union documents, in particular from the post-World War II period of internal struggle between the union's Communist and anti-Communist factions. There are also files on the Spring and Fall Strikes (1936-37), the Marine Workers Industrial Union, and the Mariners Club of the Communist Party. Individuals represented by files, many of whom were at one time Communist Party members, include Danny Boano, Johnny Gladstone, Roy Hudson, Charles Keith, Al Lannon, Barney and Greta Lynch, Bob McElroy, Gilbert Mers, Blackie (Frederick N.) Myers, Tommy Ray, Al Richmond, Harry Rubin, Joe Stack, and Arnold Weissflog. Also of note is an incomplete run (1951-1986) of the Dockers News, a rank and file newsletter by members of the International Longshoremens Association in New York. Also included are several typescripts of historical recollections and reminiscences by some of the abovementioned individuals. Throughout are a number of individual and group photographs of radical sailors and longshemen, including Bill Bailey and Harry Hynes.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged alphabetically by topic.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Bruce Nelson in 2011. The accession number 2011.085 is associated with this gift.
Bailey, Bill; Boano, Danny; Bridges, Harry, 1901-; Communist Party of the United States of America. Mariners Club.; Communist Party of the United States of America. Waterfront Section.; Curran, Joseph Edwin, 1906-1981; Dockers News (New York, N.Y.).; Gladstone, John, 1917-; Hudson, Roy; Hynes, Harry, d. 1937; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union.; International Longshoremen's Association.; International Seamen's Union of America.; Keith, Charles; Marine Workers Industrial Union (U.S.).; McElroy, Bob; Myers, Frederick N.; National Maritime Union of America.; NMU Pilot.; Ray, Tommy; Richmond, Al, 1913-1987.; Smith, Ferdinand; Stack, Joe--Interviews.; Interviews.; Labor unions and communism |z United States.; Merchant mariners |x Labor unions |z United States.; Merchant mariners |z United States |v Interviews.; Oral histories (document genres); Photographs.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, American.; Stevedores |z New York (State) |z New York |v Drama.; Transcripts.
- Bailey, Bill: Photographs (2 group portraits featuring ailey, including one shipboard on return from Spanish Civil War); Bailey's Carnet Afiliado for the International Brigades; "Frisco's Grand Old Red (San Francisco Sunday Examiner, (6/26/88); "A Party for Bill Bailey (Program, 1/12/1992), 1938-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Boano, Danny (NMU Activist): Correspondence; Memoirs (Mobile, AL, 1945 NMU Convention); Oral History (detailed summary), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Davis, Nathan (NMU General Organizer): Letter to Joseph Curran, et. al., re Great Lakes Organizing, Dec 20, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
- Dockers News (Publication of ILA Rank and File), 1951-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Fall Strike: Fliers, Minutes of Striking Maritime Workers (Stuyvvesant High School, NYC, Jan 28, 1937), 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Gladstone, Johnny: Letter to NMU Pilot re S.S. San Jose, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Gladstone, Johnny: Letters to Bruce Nelson, Jack McCusker, Bob McElroy, Tom Walker, 1979-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5A)
- Gladstone, Johnny: "Reflections on the Generation of 1936-1946,"Musings on May Day," and other recollections, 1986-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5B)
- Gladstone, Johnny: Trial and Expulsion from NMU, Feb 25, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5C)
- Gladstone, Johnny: Untitled Report [pp. 8-23], re Great Lakes, Gulf Coast, NMU in General, circa 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5D)
- Gladstone, Johnny: Letter to Bill Bailey (1/30/90); Letter to Joe Doyle (6/18/86); "Neo_Nazism and Academic Freedom at the University of Miami" (4/12/94); "Cool Air for Florida" ( South Florida History, Spring, 1996) (Box 1, Folder 5E)
- (re) Hall, Paul: "The Street Smarts of a Seafaring Man" by Phil Tracy, Village Voice, circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- The Hook: Issued by Rankd and File Members, Local 1258. International Longshoremens Association (NY). Contents: Vol 1, nos. 1,2,3,4,6; Vol 2, nos. 1, 2, 2(special issue) (Box 1, Folder 6A)
- Hudson, Roy: Printed Ephemera; Research notes, "In Memory of Roy Hudson," by Bruce Nelson, 1940s, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Hynes, Harry: Photographs (2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- International Longshoremens Association: Rank and File Fliers and Leaflets, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Kagel, Sam: "The 1934 General Strike as Told by Sam Kagel" (16 pp.), Sep 1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Keith, Charles: Daily Worker Article on His Expulsion from CPUSA (Jan 19, 1946); Obituaries (1976), Jan 19, 1946-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Lannon, Al: Letters from Ferdinand Smith to Maritime Committee for the Defense of Al Lannon, etc., All Lannon letter (1968) to Bernard Raskin (NMU), re the latter's On a True Course, 1951-1952, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Lynch, Barney and Greta: Greta [Kornfeld} Honorary #1 Strike Picket Card, International Seamen's Union, Nov 1, 1936; Photographs (5): Two group photos (seamen on pier, 1936[?]); NMU Semi-Annual Conference, Jul 28, 1942; Harry Bridges Being Visited in Hospital, 1936-1942, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Mariners Club (CPUSA): New York Post Articles (1938); Dies Committee Testimony of Seaman Frederick C. Phillips [1939?], 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Marine Workers Industrial Union: Notes, Re-typed Excerpts from Various Sources, Reprints, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- McElroy, Bob: Notes on Conversation With, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- McElroy, Bob: Photograph (group portrait with BM on right), Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Mers, Gilbert (Gulf Coast Longshoreman and Communist): Letters to Bruce Nelson; Nelson Review of Mers' Working the Waterfront (1988), 1990, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Myers, Blackie [Frederick N.]: Membership Books (1936); Confidential Letter from Harry [Bridges, 1943; "Metehods Used by Stool Pidgeons in the NMU"; NMU Charges v. Myers (1949); Correspondence with NMU re Retirement (1950-51); Research Notes; Obituaries, 1936-1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- National Maritime Union: Printed Ephemera, 1936-1950 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Nelson, Bruce: Letter for the Founding of the Marine Workers Historical Association, Nov 25, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Nelson, Bruce: Divided We Stand (Description of), 2001 (Box 1, Folder 21A)
- Nelson, Bruce: Letters to Tamiment Library Accompanying and Describing Materials Donated, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 21B)
- Nelson, Bruce: Writings, Published, 1984-1996 (Box 1, Folder 21C)
- NMU Pilot: Letters from Rank and File Radicals; Column by Joe Curran re Committee for Maritime Unity, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Photograph: Crew of S.S. Rutland Victory (Holding NMU Pilot Issue Headlined "Strike Vote May 4"), Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Photographs: Joe Curran (2), Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Photograph: Group Portrait Aboard Unidentified Ship, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24A)
- Photographs (3): Freddy Reed 91940?); Fred Barnecoat and Johnny Gladstone (1941?); Sinking of Graf Spee (1939), 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 24B)
- Post Cards (2): Hunger March, Chicago, May 1, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 24C)
- Postek, Stanley: Letter to Bruce Nelson, Jun 17, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Ray, Tommy: Letter to New York Times (1950): Correspondence with Bruce Nelson (1978-1979), 1950-1979 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Richmond, Al: Letters to Bruce Nelson; Comments on Nelson's Manuscript; Obituaries, 1978-1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Rubin, Harry: Letter to "Spargoh[?], 1949; Correspondence with Bruce Nelson, 1979, 1949-1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Salcido, Antonio (Tony): Transcript of Telephone Interview with Bruce Nelson, Jun 2, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- San Francisco Labor Council: 1883-1983: A Century of Progress, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Smith, Ferdinand; Other 1948n NMU Election Materials (Box 2, Folder 2A)
- Spring Strike: Photocopies of International Seamens Union (ISU) Documnets; Typed Versions of Daily Worker Articles, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Stack, Joseph: Address to the Maritime Workers Historical Association Meeting (NYC): Includes Discussion of S.S. California in San Pedro in March, 1936, Dec 1, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Stack, Joseph: Correspondence, Notes, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Stack, Joseph: Transcript of Inteview with Bruce Nelson, Nov 26, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Stack, Joseph: Letter from Nathan Davis (NMU General Organizer) re Great Lakes Area, Nov 21, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6A)
- Standard, William L. (NMU General Counsel): Address to Second Biennial Convention of the NMU, Jul 1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Strike Committees (flier) Port of NY: Marine Firemens Union, Marine Cooks and Stewards Union, Oct 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7A)
- Tobin, Patrick (ILWU Washington DC Representative): Correspondence with Bruce Nelson, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Weissflog, Arno: Bruce Nelson Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Weissflog, Arno: Letters to NMU re Reinstatement of His Pension Rights, 1969, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- re Weissflog, Arno [?]: "Unknown Sailor" by Alvah Bessie (in the New Masses), Feb 17, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Weissflog, Arno: U.S. Coast Guard Regection of Request for Merchant Seaman Documents, Mar 17, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 12)